This great war began from a single confrontation.
たった一つのきっかけから　争いが始まり
とても大きな戦争に発展しました
Many different people with different ideals have clashed, bringing forth great tragedy.
様々な人の様々な思いがすれ違い
大きな不幸を生みました
And that is truly regrettable.
それは　とても悲しいことです
私は　この戦争を憂い
I too have suffered from this war.
I feel both shame and regret for our use of a power not meant for human hands.
人の手に余る大きな力の扱いについて反省とともに
深く後悔をしています
And so, here and now...
私は　今ここに
I claim my birthright to Rayregalia Vers Rayvers's title
先代皇帝　レイレガリア・ヴァース・レイヴァースの後を継ぎ
and hereby name myself Empress of Vers.
ヴァース帝国の女王になります
そして　軌道騎士37家門の一人　クルーテオ伯爵を夫に迎えます
I also announce my engagement to Count Cruhteo of the Orbital Knights' Thirty-Seven Clans.
As the imperial family of the Vers Empire,
we hereby extend the olive branch of peace to Earth.
我々ヴァース帝国王室は　地球との和平を望みます
In the name of the Empress of Vers,
ヴァース帝国女王の名において
I order all Orbital Knights
whom this broadcast may reach
この放送を聞いている全軌道騎士に
to cease hostilities at once.
即時停戦を命じます
What is this?
バカな…
Was the princess not poised to found a new dynasty with Count Troyard?
アセイラム姫殿下は　トロイヤード卿と新王朝を築くのではなかったのか
What will we do about the all-out offensive against Earth?
連合軍への総攻撃は…
Halt it.
待て
Put the forces on standby.
今は動くな　風がどちらに吹くか静観する
Let us await further developments.
It is no wonder.
やはりな
Count Troyard is still little more than Terran rabble.
所詮　トロイヤード卿は下賤な地球の生まれ
Ascension to royalty was always beyond his reach.
王室と関わろうなど恐れ多いわ
What is this?
どういうことだ　これは…
Sir Harklight, we withdraw to the moon!
ハークライト卿　帰投するぞ
Sir Slaine...
スレイン様
本字幕由诸神字幕组出品，仅供学习交流，禁止用于商业用途
更多中日双语字幕，尽在 i.kamigami.org 和微博 @诸神字幕组
日听:ikiko&Archer  翻译:mam&郝郝
校对:安少&zwx  时间轴:FoH2O  压制:河蟹
Why are they still fighting?
なんでまだ戦ってるの？
お姫様が戦争やめるって宣言したのよ
The princess ordered them to stand down!
月面基地の軍はやる気満々よ
The forces from the moon base still want to fight.
みんな　気を抜かないで　戦争は終わってないわよ
Stay focused!
The battle isn't over yet!
You hear that?
聞いたかい
Yeah...
That Princess Asseylum just now—
さっきのアセイラム姫…
アセイラム女王は　私の知ってるお姫様でした
I mean, Empress Asseylum—
sounded just like the one I remember.
Yeah.
界塚少尉の推測通りということですか
So it's just as Second Lieutenant Kaizuka predicted.
では　停戦の命令も本物？
Then that order for a ceasefire must be real as well.
The enemies we're engaging
aren't standing down, though.
目の前の敵は　戦いをやめるつもりはないみたいですよ
Any word from HQ?
司令部からは？
No new orders.
指示はありません　作戦続行っす
So we're to continue the operation.
Neither the moon base nor the Landing Castles show any intent to cease hostilities.
月面基地及び揚陸城は　まだ停戦の意思を見せていません
Where is Empress Asseylum?
アセイラム女王の所在は？
The earlier transmission was broadcast from Count Mazuurek's Landing Castle.
先ほどの通信は　マズゥールカ伯爵の揚陸城から発信されました
月を見捨てたか
Did she abandon the moon?
Or has a schism developed?
それとも割れたのか
Count Troyard, how are we to proceed with Her Highness' orders?
トロイヤード伯爵　アセイラム様の号令は…
号令？
Orders?
What orders?
何のことだ
失礼しました
Apologies, my lord.
まさかな　そんな手を使うとは
I'm impressed.
This is an unexpected turn of events.
レムリナ姫
Princess Lemrina.
What truly matters is royal blood.
本当に大切なのは　王族の血
アルドノアの起動権さえあれば
As long as you have Aldnoah activation rights,
あなたの夢は叶うのではなくて
your dream is still within reach.
私ならどこへも行きませんよ
I will stay with you.
This is the only place I can call home.
私の居場所は　ここしかないのですから
だから…
So please...
You are right.
そうですね
I thank you for your kindness, Princess Lemrina.
ご厚情　感謝します　レムリナ姫
Let's be off.
行きましょう
はい
Yes, let's.
It's so beautiful.
綺麗ですね
Was that a heartless thing to say?
不謹慎でしょうか　こんな…
私は　あの光の中を飛びながら　いろいろなものを見ました
I've seen many things while flying through those lights.
いろいろなものって？
Many things?
The future.
未来です
未来？
The future?
The good and the bad alike.
よいこと　悪いことすべて
All I could see was the immediate future,
見えるものは　ほんの少し先のことだけ
but I thought I understood everything.
何でも分かるつもりでいました
多くのことはそのとおりだった
Many things unfolded just as I foresaw,
でも…
but...
I lost sight of what was truly important.
本当に大切なものは　何も見えていませんでした
Resupply.
補給を
Yes, sir!
はっ
トロイヤード卿
Count Troyard!
一体どういうことだ　アセイラム姫殿下はどうして…
What is the meaning of this?
Why would Princess Asseylum say such things?
Sir Slaine...
スレイン様
Patch me through to the command center.
司令室に繋げろ　全軍に通達する
I will address all units,
including the Stygis Platoon out in the field.
出撃中のステイギス隊にもだ
Yes, sir!
はっ
聞け　総員10分以内に月面基地より離脱
Listen up!
You have ten minutes to evacuate the moon base!
揚陸城とともに　連合軍に投降せよ
Surrender to the Earth forces
together with the Landing Castles!
We are abandoning the moon base!
この月面基地を放棄する
気は確かか
Are you out of your mind?
Slaine!
スレイン
Princess Lemrina...
レムリナ姫　これまでの数々のご無礼
Let me apologize for the many wrongs
大変失礼いたしました
I have rendered unto you.
スレイン
Slaine...
どうか　いつまでもお健やかに
I pray for your well-being.
Harklight, escort Her Highness to a shuttle.
ハークライト　レムリナ姫をシャトルへお連れしろ
ご命令のままに
As you wish.
Slaine! Stop!
いや　スレイン
Please come with me, Your Highness.
姫様　どうぞこちらへ
No! I won't leave!
私は行きません
Slaine! Slaine!
スレイン　スレイン
月面基地より　新たな機影多数
We're detecting numerous craft exiting the moon base!
Reinforcements?
援軍ですか
それが…
No.
They're leaving the combat area.
戦闘宙域から離れていきます
The moon base...
月面基地が…
陥落？
is going down?
Did we beat them?
やっつけたの？
No...
違う
They're self-destructing?
自爆？
ハークライト様？
Sir Harklight?
Guard the shuttle.
シャトルの護衛を頼む
ハークライト様
Sir Harklight!
Harklight.
ハークライト　何をしている　戻れ
What are you doing? Turn back.
I thought I ordered you to surrender.
投降しろと言ったはずだ
Harklight!
ハークライト
ステイギス隊　勝手な真似をするな
Stygis Squadron! Don't act on your own!
Reinforcements closing in.
敵増援部隊接近　10時の方向　仰角マイナス10
Enemy at ten o'clock, ten degrees down!
Stand by to engage!
応戦準備
Stop! We no longer have any hope of winning!
止せ　我々にもはや勝機はない
Don't throw your lives away!
命を無駄にするな
I made my peace with death long ago.
とうに覚悟はできております
わがまま　どうかお許しください
Please allow me this one selfish act.
投降するんだ　ハークライト
Surrender, Harklight!
申し訳ありませんが　スレイン様
Forgive me, Sir Slaine.
But I cannot comply with that order.
その命令はお受けできません
Here they come!
来るぞ
All units, scatter!
全機散開
Come on!
このぉ…
なんてことを
How could they do this?
Damn it all!
くそ
What's that?
何だ
Those moves...
あの動きは…
そうだな　ハークライト
You're right, Harklight.
このまま終わるわけにはいかない
We can't let it end like this.
僕にはやることが　まだ
There's still something I have to do.
I've come for you, Slaine Troyard.
迎えに来た　スレイン・トロイヤード
Let's settle this once and for all, Kaizuka Inaho!
決着をつけるぞ　界塚伊奈帆
Reading my moves won't do you any good if you can't get away from them.
どんなに攻撃を予測しようと
逃げられなければ意味はない
You're the one who isn't getting away!
逃げられないのは　お前だ
Opening contact channel.
接触回線オープン　プロトコル解析
Decrypting protocols.
I doubt this will do any good, but I'll ask anyway.
無駄だと思うが　一応聞く
Will you surrender, Slaine Troyard?
降伏しろ　スレイン・トロイヤード
Did you come all this way just to
tell me poor jokes, Kaizuka Inaho?
そんなつまらないことをわざわざ言いに来たのか　界塚伊奈帆
いや　目的は別だ
No. I have a different objective.
I'm glad to hear that.
嬉しいよ
Don't disappoint me, now!
そう来なくては
Damn! My monitors are damaged?
くそ　量子アンテナにダメージが
I know. We can't do any more high-load processing.
もう負荷の大きな処理は無理か
Cut all predictive imagers.
予測イメージをすべてカットだ
I no longer...
もう僕に…
need a future!
未来なんて必要ない
Incoming at two o'clock, five degrees up!
2時の方向　仰角5　来ます
All ahead, emergency speed!
左舷前進強速　回頭060
Come about, 060!
Coming about, 060!
回頭060
Load canister shot!
キャニスター弾装填　照準次第発射
Fire once targets are locked!
Wow...
すごっ
Nao's combat data is stored in the tactical data link.
戦術データリンクに　なお君の戦闘データが保存されてるわ
All units, refer to that and—
各自参照して…
Yuki!
ユキさん
大丈夫
I'm okay!
Barouhcruz of the Orbital Knights' Thirty-Seven Clans reporting.
ヴァース軌道騎士37家門　バルークルス
May I intrude?
押してまいる
バルークルス伯爵
Count Barouhcruz...
Incoming at eight o'clock, twenty-five degrees down!
8時の方向　仰角マイナス25　来ます
迎撃を…
Intercept!
任せろ
I've got this!
残弾数　3
Three rounds remaining.
There is nothing to be gained by continuing to fight.
これ以上戦っても得るものはない
Agreed. But there is nothing to be lost, either.
ああ　だが　失うものもない
Giving in to despair is a foolish choice.
自暴自棄は愚かな選択だ
You just don't get it!
分かってないな
This is precisely what I've wanted all along!
これはもっとも求めた選択だ
刻め
Slice them to ribbons!
Rayet!
ライエ
Fool!
愚か者が
急接近する機影あり
Radar returns approaching fast!
何
What?
It's the Tharsis... and a Terran Cataphract!
タルシスと　地球軍のカタフラクトです
That's...
あれは…
Rayet!
ライエ
Three-direction crossfire!
三方十字砲火
MRSI　機体制圧　オートショット
MRSI, neutralize target, auto fire!
I've always...
ずっと…
I've always loathed...
ずっと目障りだったんだ
that wretched color!
その色が
Sir Harklight!
ハークライト卿
The drones are on autopilot! Use the rocks!
オプションは自動操縦だ　岩石を利用しろ
攻撃の方向を限定できる
We can limit the direction of their attack!
Are you all right?
大丈夫か
Yes. I only lost an arm.
ええ　片腕を失っただけです
ハークライト様
Sir Harklight!
Battle status?
戦況は？
Three Stygis Masters remain, myself included,
私を含めて　ステイギスマスターの残りが3機
as well as some six Slaves.
スレイブ6機ほどです
他は地球軍に墜とされました
The rest have been felled by Terran forces.
こちらもバレットがほぼ撃ち尽くしたが
And I am perilously low on ammunition.
バルークルス伯爵
Count Barouhcruz.
オクタンティスの右腕が効かぬ
The Octantis' right arm is out of commission.
It must have been damaged in that last attack.
どうやら先程の攻撃でやられたらしい
なかなかやるものだな　地球の連中も
These Terran warriors are not without skill.
Indeed.
ええ　スレイン様の生まれ故郷ですから
I should expect as much from Sir Slaine's birthplace.
オリンポスの砂嵐には抗うなかれか
"Fight not an Olympus sandstorm," eh?
We seem to have misread the winds.
風を読み間違えたらしい
Let us join in battle once again!
もう一戦行くか
I shall accompany you.
お供します
Enemy formation closing in at
nine o'clock, twenty degrees up!
9時の方向　仰角20　敵機編隊が接近
全砲門　狙え
All guns, take aim!
Cataphract platoons: all units fire at will!
カタフラクト隊　全機一斉射撃
ドラッグシュートの代わりだ　機体を安定させる
I'll act as a drogue chute.
It will stabilize your descent.
一緒に死ぬつもりか
You intend to die with me?
We'll burn up on re-entry.
燃え尽きるぞ
Cataphract frames are high density.
カタフラクトのフレームは高密度だ
They'll work well enough as ablative shielding.
アブレータとして十分に働く
まさか　不可能だ
Impossible. They'll never last.
さあ　どうかな
You think so? I guess we'll see.
お姉ちゃん　あれ…
Look at that, Sis!
A shooting star!
流れ星
Special report.
ご覧ください
Aldnoah Reactor #1, constructed as a sign of goodwill between Earth and Vers,
地球とヴァースの友好の証として建造されたアルドノア1号炉が
is scheduled to be activated today.
本日起動される運びとなりました
今回はアセイラム女王自ら起動式典に参加されるとのことですが
We're told that Empress Asseylum herself
will participate in the activation ceremony.
Research into unrestricted activation privileges for all is still ongoing.
起動権を普遍化し　誰でも起動できる研究も進んでいるとか
When that is achieved, it will signal
the birth of Aldnoah-based industries
そうなれば　アルドノアを使った産業も発展し
that will help greatly with
the Earth's reconstruction.
地球の復興にも大きく寄与するでしょう
アルドノアを産出するヴァース帝国にとっても
And for the Vers Empire,
provider of Aldnoah technology,
it should prove an effective means
to earn foreign capital.
外貨を稼ぐ有力な手段となりますね
Dr. Troyard's theories have already been proven,
トロイヤード博士の理論は既に実証されていますので
so we should see them put into practice
in the near future.
近い将来　実現することでしょう
It's ironic that Slaine Troyard,
そのトロイヤード博士の息子
the son of that same Dr. Troyard, was the one who plotted the assassination of Empress Asseylum
スレイン・トロイヤードがアセイラム女王の暗殺を目論み
and served as the trigger for Interplanetary War II.
第二次惑星間戦争の発端を作ったというのは
何とも皮肉なことです
Slaine Troyard's death allowed Earth and Vers
to settle upon a friendship treaty.
スレイン・トロイヤードが死亡したことで
地球とヴァースは友好条約を結んだわけですが…
However, there are still Mars Knights who continue to occupy territory on Earth.
未だに地上を占拠する火星騎士も残っていますからね
今回のアセイラム女王の来訪は彼らとの和平交渉も目的に入ってます
One goal of Empress Asseylum's visit
is peace negotiations with those knights.
Here's hoping that we'll see the prompt return
of that occupied territory.
占領された地域の早期返還に期待したいですね
May this light
この輝きが地球とヴァースの平和の架け橋になることを願って
form a bridge of peace between Earth and Vers.
目覚めよ
Awaken!
How are you feeling?
調子は？
悪くはなさそうだ
You don't look too bad.
でも食事はちゃんと取った方がいい
You really should eat your meals, though.
I've had complaints from the warden.
刑務官がぼやいていた
キミの番だ
Your move.
その目
Your eye...
僕が撃った傷か？
Is that from when I shot you?
アナリティカルエンジン
I replaced it with an analytical engine.
脳細胞に神経接続された生体デバイスを埋め込んでいたんだ
A biomechanical implant that was neuro-linked to my cranial nerves.
But I had it removed. I don't need it anymore.
でも外した
もういらないから
Hasn't this gone long enough?
もういいだろ
I deceived. I stole. I killed.
騙した　奪った　殺した
I sacrificed countless numbers of my own.
多くの仲間を犠牲にした
Please.
頼む…
No. You're going to live.
ダメだ　キミは生きるんだ
Why?
どうして
Why did you save me?!
どうして僕を助けた
I have one more request.
もう一つ　お願いがあります
It wasn't my decision.
僕じゃない
アセイラム姫の意志だ
It was Princess Asseylum's.
Please...
どうか…
Please, save Slaine.
どうかスレインを
Save Slaine Troyard.
スレイン・トロイヤードを救ってあげてください
彼を　不幸の連鎖から…
Save him from the cycle of misery.
どうか
I beg you.
Seylum asked me...
セラムさんが…
キミを救ってくれと
to save you.
すごい
Incredible.
どこまでも続く青い空と海
The blue sky and ocean go on as far as the eye can see!
It's so beautiful.
なんと美しい
空が青いのはレイリー散乱によるものだそうです
I'm told that the blue sky is the result
of something called Rayleigh scattering.
お詳しいですね
You're quite well-informed.
When I visited Earth last time,
以前地球を訪れた際に親しくなった地球の方から教えていただきました
a Terran I had befriended
was kind enough to teach me.
It's a cherished memory of mine.
美しい思い出です
kimi ga miru yume wa
Your selfless dream
君が見る夢は　古いインクで紙に書いた祈りのよう
furui inku de kami ni kaita inori no you
is like a prayer written on paper with yellowing ink
chiisana sono te ga sugaru mono mo
Your fragile hands seek support,
小さなその手が縋るものも　今はまだ何処にも無い
ima wa mada doko ni mo nai
and yet have nothing at all to cling to
sore demo kimi no yuku michi wo
But even so, I want to guard
それでも君の行く道を
kirei na mono wa kirei na mama de
the path you walk
奇麗なものは奇麗なままで　守り続けたいと思うよ
mamoritsuzuketai to omou yo
in all my beauty
sora to mizu ga hoshi wo somete
I can see our skies and seas in the stars
空と水が星を染めて
awaku niji wo egaite chitte
before they fall to make a rainbow
淡く虹を描いて散って
mabushii yoru kimi ga utau
Light tears through the night and you sing
眩しい夜　君が歌う
koe wa doko made todoku no darou
How far will your voice travel?
声は何処まで届くのだろう
akogare no sumau aoi hoshi no hikari
This is the light of the blue planet I admire,
憧れの住まう蒼い星のひかり
tada bokura wa koi wo shite
the light that we love helplessly
ただ僕らは恋をして
tatta hitotsu no mirai no tame ni
We sacrifice all we have at our disposal
たったひとつの未来の為に
ima no subete kanadetemiru
for the only future we have left
今の全て奏でている
kimi ga yume miru nara
When you dream,
君が夢見るなら
soba ni tatte
I will stand next to you
側に立って　同じ彼方へ手を伸ばすよ
onaji kanata he te wo nobasu yo
and reach for the same point on the horizon
kimi ga shinjita shizuka na sora ni
One day, I might be able
君が信じた静かな空に
itsuka boku mo todoku darou
to see the sky you put so much faith into:
いつか僕も届くだろう
doko made mo mabushii
as far as the eye can see,
何処までも眩しい　heavenly blue
heavenly blue